Okay, so the American Revolution is won
and now it's time to create some brand
spanking new state and federal
governments here in these United States.
And I don't know about you, but I am so
down to talk about that. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay. Now, as a result
of declaring independence in 1776, each
state drafted and ratified a new
constitution to create their state level
government. And because during the
revolution, there was no central
government aside from the Continental
Congress, which had very little power.
State governments played a significant
role in carrying on the fight for
independence. Now, it's going to be
important to understand some of the
common features of these state
constitutions because they're going to
play a real big role in the creation of
the constitution later. But alas, I get
ahead of myself. Oh, and by the way, if
you want note guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos, then get
your clicky finger out and check the
link in the description. Now, in
general, Virginia's constitution, which
included a bill of rights, became a
loose template for other state
constitutions. And among the rights
protected in Virginia's constitution
were the freedom of the press, free
elections, the right to form militias,
right to a speedy trial, etc. It was
also common that state constitutions
banned titles of nobility and other
social symbols of aristocracy. And
that's not surprising given the
enlightenment emphasis on the rejection
of arbitrary hereditary power. Now, for
the most part, state constitutions
limited the franchise or, you know,
voting rights to white male property
owners. And it's not hard to understand
why the franchise was limited to white
men. And if that is hard to understand,
then I would direct you to my previous
video, my dear people. But why property
requirements? Like what's that about?
Well, let me compare it to the stock
market. Like if I purchase a stock or a
share in a company, then I also have
voting rights regarding what that
company does. And that's real important
because I'm invested in that company
making money so that I too can make
money with my shares. But if someone
doesn't own shares in the company, then
it doesn't matter how many opinions
about the company pour forth from that
person's mouth hole because they are not
invested. And that's the idea of
property requirements for voting. Those
who own land were considered to be those
who had invested in society and
therefore could be trusted to vote on
the outcomes of society. I mean, I'm not
saying I agree with it. I'm just trying
to explain it to you. So, you know, you
smell what I'm stepping in? Good.
Because the third commonality in the
various state constitutions that you're
going to need to know is that with the
exception of Vermont, state
constitutions did almost nothing to
eradicate slavery from their midst.
However, to be fair, some states did
adopt constitutional measures for the
gradual emancipation of enslaved people.
The chief example being Pennsylvania.
Okay. Fourth, and finally, state
constitutions create a government in
which most of the power was concentrated
in the legislature, which was the
representative body of the people as
opposed to an executive or, you know,
like a governor. Furthermore, almost all
state representative bodies were bicame
and that indicates that after so long
enduring what they considered the
tyranny of arbitrary executive power in
the hands of stupid Great Britain, the
new state constitutions wanted to
decentralize power as much as possible.
Okay, so state governments unlocked. But
after the revolution, the United States
needed a new federal government as well.
And so in 1777, the Continental Congress
drafted the first constitution of the
United States, namely the Articles of
Confederation. And yes, you heard me
right. the Constitution of the United
States that you know is in fact the
second constitution to govern this fair
land. And the fact that there's now a
different constitution should tell you
that the articles was kind of a hot
smoking turd. I mean that sounds a
little judgy, but just let me tell you
about it. Now, the structure of the
Articles of Confederation reflected the
state's distaste for executive and
centralized power. And even though the
Articles created a federal government
which united the states, it kept the
federal government exceedingly weak. And
that's not hard to understand because
the folks who composed this document
still had kind of a monarchy hangover
from their colonial days. And so they
created a central government that was
about as threatening as a soft bone
toddler who likes warm hugs. Therefore,
in the first years of the New Republic,
state governments had by far the most
political power. Now, I'm as eager as
you are to start talking about the
weaknesses of the articles and all the
drama there unto appertaining. But
first, I need to tell you about what was
arguably the best achievement of the
federal government during this era,
namely the passage of the Northwest
Ordinance of 1787. Sounds really
exciting, I know, but it was. You see,
the purpose of this ordinance was to
organize and regulate the vast and
unsettled western territory that had
come to the United States as a result of
the Treaty of Paris. And so, not only
did the ordinance mandate that land be
reserved for schools, but it also banned
slavery in the territory. Additionally,
it laid out the rules that dictated how
territories in the western region could
become official states. And it worked
marvelously. In fact, if you live in any
of these states right here, well, then
you could thank the Northwest Ordinance
of 1787. Okay. Now, while this limited
federal power satisfied Americans who
wanted to avoid centralized power at all
costs, the republic began facing
significant problems that began to show
the weaknesses of the articles to
effectively govern. For example, under
the articles, the federal government was
composed of a single body, namely a
legislature, which is to say, there was
no federal executive and there was no
federal court system. Additionally, the
federal government had no power to tax
the states unless all 13 states agreed
to be taxed, nor did it have the power
to create a national currency or raise a
national army. And beyond that, there
were at least five seats on the
constitutional struggle bus that kept
revealing cracks in the article. The
first seat on that bus was problems with
international trade. You see, after the
Revolutionary War, Great Britain cut off
trade between the United States and the
British West Indies. Rude.
>> And then Spain went ahead and prohibited
American trade ships from accessing the
Mississippi River via Louisiana.
>> Guys, stop.
>> And pirates off the barbar coast of
North Africa attacked US merchant ships.
But the federal government, with its
glaring lack of centralized power, not
to mention a navy, was helpless to
remedy these economic problems. Okay.
The second seat on the bus was all about
federal finances. Put simply, the new
Congress could not pay its war debts.
You remember a minute ago when I said
the articles gave the federal government
no power to tax? Yeah. If Congress
wanted tax revenue, they just kind of
had to knock on each state's door and
ask nicely. And you know, you don't have
to be a genius to figure out how that
went. Hey guys, sorry to bother you, but
uh can we have some money?
Just you so crazy. What this guy? So to
remedy this problem, states proposed a
resolution in 1782 which granted
Congress the power to collect a 5% tax
on imported goods. 11 states approved,
but those rascally states, Rhode Island
and Virginia, said no. And for that law
to pass, a unanimous vote was required,
another weakness of the Articles of
Confederation. And since they didn't get
it, Congress remained weak and broke.
Okay. The third seat on the Federal
Struggle bus had to do with interstate
commerce, or you know, the way states
trade with each other. Now, because the
new nation was more like a collection of
independent and powerful states, they
each competed with one another for
economic gain. To that end, states put
tariffs on goods and hampered free trade
in and around the new republic. And as
you may have guessed by now, the federal
government under the articles had
precisely no authority to settle
disputes over interstate commerce and
help facilitate the flourishing of a
national economy. Okay. The fourth seat
on the struggle bus was reserved for
problems with foreign relations. You
see, although Great Britain had lost the
Revolutionary War, they kept forces
occupying several forts along the
Western Frontier. Dirty move. And here
they traded guns and other valuable
items to American Indian groups and then
encouraged them to attack frontier
settlers in order to frustrate their
progress west. I'll just keep getting
dirty. And can you guess who was
basically powerless to address this?
>> George Washington.
>> What? No. No. It had to do with Rosa
Park.
>> Stop it. No. It was in fact the federal
government under the Articles of
Confederation which had no power to stop
this egregious violation of the terms of
peace. And why? Because as I mentioned
earlier, Congress had no authority to
raise an army. And now we come to the
fifth seat on the federal struggle bus.
That one was reserved for internal
unrest. And oh my goodness, if the other
problems showed cracks in the Articles
of Confederation, this is the one that
blew its entire crap up. So, let me tell
you about Shea's rebellion. Now, in the
years following the revolution, Congress
had still not paid many of the men who
had fought in the revolution and they
were suffering profoundly. And so,
finally fed up with this situation, a
group of angry farmers in Massachusetts
led by the saucy Daniel Shaes attacked
courouses in the area and then stormed a
federal arsenal. Long story short, the
Massachusetts militia met the rebels and
quickly suppressed the rebellion. Now,
that may seem like a small deal by your
reckoning, but it was a big slap in the
face to those in power in the era of the
Articles. You see, the chief effect of
this rebellion was to put on full
display the intolerable weakness of the
Articles of Confederation because the
federal government could do precisely
squat about it. And furthermore, because
there were unpaid veterans everywhere in
the States, fears were stoked that this
rebellion could be the start of many
more to follow. And so when they
considered that the federal government
could do precisely nothing to remedy
this problem, I mean like they couldn't
neither pay the veterans nor raise an
army to defeat them, it became clear
that a new constitution was sorely
needed. And that, my dear pupil, is
where we'll pick up next time. Well,
okay. You can click here to watch my
other unit 3 videos, or you can click
here to grab my video note guides, which
will help you get all the contents of
this course firmly crammed into your
brain, folks. And I appreciate you
stopping by, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm out.